Guide to the Erica Van Horn Prints
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Erica Van Horn prints.
1976-1999
1976-1981
YCAL MSS 340
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.17
(1 oversize box and 16 broadside folders)
This collection consists of unique prints created by Erica Van Horn. The prints complement her one-of-a-kind books and other printed work. The prints are chiefly etchings combined with chine collé on watercolor paper, as well as monoprints that depict Saint Sebastian. Each of the prints has title and a signature or signed initials inscribed by Van Horn.
Van Horn, Erica, 1954-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Erica Van Horn on the Elizabeth Wakeman Dwight Memorial Fund, 2009.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Erica Van Horn (born 1954)
Erica Van Horn was born in Concord, New Hampshire. The American artist, writer, and bookmaker graduated with a Master of Fine Arts in Printmaking from the School of the Art Institute of Chicago. She uses the portability of the printed sheet, mostly in book form, to construct a narrative around the incidental parts of her life. The work now mostly issues through Coracle, a small publishing press based in Ireland, which she directs with Simon Cutts (born 1944), writer, artist, and editor.
Description of the Papers
This collection consists of unique prints created by Erica Van Horn. The prints complement her one-of-a-kind books and other printed work. The prints are chiefly etchings combined with chine collé on watercolor paper, as well as monoprints that depict Saint Sebastian. Each of the prints has title and a signature or signed initials inscribed by Van Horn.
Arrangement
Organized into one series: I. Prints, 1976-1999.
Printmakers; Prints -- 20th Century; Chine collé prints -- Color; Etchings; Monoprints (painting and printing works); Van Horn, Erica, 1954-; Sebastian, Saint -- Pictorial works
- Prints, 1976-1999; Series I; 37
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically into groups designated by Van Horn and chronologically within each group.
  Scope and Contents
  Except where noted, all prints were created on Arches watercolor paper.
  - Books and Writings, 1976-1985
    Early prints created by Van Horn. In documentation acquired with the collection, she describes her work as follows:
    "Almost all of my prints at this time use the method of chine collé which is a way of collaging elements onto a piece of paper at the same time as you are printing it. Since all of my collage elements were found and saved things, every print became a unique object. Hence the term edition varieé again and again. I could use the same plates dozens of times and use the exact same method and color in my inking, but the collage elements changed each time. Occasionally, as in Republic Francaise, I burned paper towels to get an almost identical shape so that I could make a more consistent edition, but even with that, my stamps were different. I used the prints as storage for remembering things.
    The pieces, which I grouped here, combine writing and calligraphic form, usually nonsensically, to suggest the written word as form of communication. Letters and books are incorporated.
    These things preceded my book works but when the books started, they were essentially already started!"
    - España España España (artist's proof), 1976; 1 print: etching and chine collé, color; plate mark 21.1 x 28.4 cm. on sheet 32.6 x 39.0 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Republic Francaise (edition varieé), 1977; 1 print: etching and chine collé, color; plate mark 19.9 x 18.5 cm. on sheet 34.6 x 29.0 cm. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Tabloid for Thomas (edition varieé, numbered 6), 1977; 1 print: etching and chine collé, color; plate mark 8.5 x 28.8 cm. on sheet 18.5 x 36.5 cm. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Letters from Home (edition varieé, numbered 12), 1978; 1 print: etching and chine collé, color; plate mark 30.2 x 45.0 cm. on sheet 48.0 x 63.5 cm. (Box 4 (Broadside))
    - Inventory (edition varieé), 1978; 1 print: collage and chine collé; on sheet 50.0 x 35.5 cm. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Untitled (Text Across Top) (edition varieé), 1978; 1 print: etching, pencil, hand stitching and chine collé, color; on sheet 30.2 x 30.2 cm. affixed on sheet 36.5 x 36.5 cm. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Book Series No. 9 (edition varieé), 1978; 1 print: collage, hand stitching, and chine collé, color; 2 sheets of Japanese paper, both 20 x 11 cm. on sheet 50.0 x 35.5 cm. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Book Series No. 12 (edition varieé), 1978; 1 print: collage, hand stitching and chine collé, color; on sheet 50.0 x 35.5 cm. (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Comprised of a letter from Robert Scott in Punta de la Mona, Spain, on December 3, 1975
    - Message Written No. 2 (edition varieé), 1978; 1 print: etching, pencil, hand stitching and chine collé, color; plate mark 60.2 x 44.2 cm. on sheet 68.5 x 52.5 cm. (Box 9 (Broadside))
    - Message Written No. 5 (edition varieé), 1978; 1 print: etching, pencil, hand stitching, machine stitching and chine collé, color; plate mark 60.2 x 44.2 on sheet 68.5 x 52.5 cm. (Box 10 (Broadside))
    - Automatic Writing Sample (edition varieé), 1978; 1 print: etching and chine collé, color; 2 sheets, both 21.4 x 59.8 on sheet 57.0 x 66.0 cm. (Box 11 (Broadside))
    - Triangle Letter Series No. 3 (with three stamps) (edition varieé), 1978; 1 print: chine collé, color; on sheet 56.0 x 75.0 cm. (Box 12 (Broadside))
    - Triangle Letter Series No. 7 (edition varieé), 1978; 1 print: chine collé, color; on sheet 56.0 x 75.0 cm. (Box 13 (Broadside))
    - Quote (unknown edition size), 1979; 1 print: etching, black and white; on sheet 33.5 x 31.5 cm. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Calligraphic Exercise (unknown edition size), 1979; 1 print: etching, black and white; plate mark 24.7 x 24.7 cm. on sheet 36.5 x 36.5 cm. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Bookcase Study for Installation at Franklin Furnace, 1985; 1 print: monoprint, black and white; typewriter paper sheet 15.3 x 26.5 cm. affixed on sheet 30.0 x 28.5 cm. (Box 1, Folder 16)
      According to Van Horn: "This study was later translated into paint directly on a sliding door at Franklin Furnace in New York City. It was a partial list of one of a kind books to include in the show, or if they were not available to be included, they would at least be there by their title."
  - Some Buildings, 1979-1980
    - Dwelling Places (artist's proof), 1979; 1 print: etching, hand-colored with photograph corners and rubber stamps, color; plate mark 10.0 x 15.1 cm. on sheet 25.8 x 29.3 cm. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Three Choices (edition varieé, edition 3), 1980; 1 print: etching and chine collé, color; plate mark 13.9 x 15.4 cm. on sheet 23.5 x 25.0 cm. (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Accompanied by an exhibition label for the 79th Exhibition by Artists of Chicago and Vicinity, at The Art Institute of Chicago, July 4-August 16, 1981.
    - Untitled (Church with Pink Cross) (edition varieé, numbered 8), 1980; 1 print: etching with acrylic paint and cut-out, color; plate mark 22.4 x 29.6 cm. on sheet 34.5 x 41.8 cm. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - House Bed (edition varieé), 1980; 1 print: etching and chine collé, color; plate mark 32.5 x 44.8 cm. on sheet 39.7 x 51.6 cm. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Monsters and a Bird, 1981-1995
    - Big Head (With Stamps) (edition varieé), 1981; 1 print: etching and chine collé, color; plate mark 13.6 x 8.5 cm. on sheet 23.7 x 16.5 cm. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Big Head (Map) (edition varieé), 1981; 1 print: etching and chine collé, color; plate mark 13.6 x 8.5 cm. on sheet 23.6 x 16.5 cm. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Spanish Monster (edition varieé), 1981; 1 print: etching and chine collé, color; plate mark 12.3 x 14.9 cm. on sheet 26.5 x 21.9 cm. (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Mail Monster (edition varieé), 1981; 1 print: etching and chine collé, color; plate mark 12.2x 14.9 cm. on sheet 25.4 x 24.8 cm. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Dovecôte-Fenêtre (with Simon Cutts) (Edition of 15, numbered 10), 1995 December 15; 1 print: linocut and letter press, color; plate mark 12.9 x 12.9 cm. on sheet 16.6 x 16.6 in a mat 33.6 x 29.2 cm. with a letterpress caption. (Box 1, Folder 25)
      Signed on verso of mat by Van Horn and Cutts.
  - Saint Sebastian, 1987; 9 prints: monoprint, black and white; on bristol boards 64.5 x 49.5 cm. (Box 26 (Broadside)–34 (Broadside))
    Consists of print numbers 10, 11, 14, 15, 20, 22, 23, 25, and 26.
  - Miscellaneous, 1976-1999
    - Chinese Puzzle Landscape-Landscape Puzzle (edition varieé), 1976; 1 print: etching and chine collé, color; plate mark in puzzle piece shape 34.6 x 22.4 cm. on sheet 50.0 x 34.1 cm. (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - McCall's 8132 (edition varieé), 1976; 1 print: etching and chine collé, color; plate mark 45.0 x 57.5 cm. on sheet 54.7 x 71.4 cm. (Folder 36 (Broadside))
    - 15 Blackthorns (Edition of 100, Numbered 36), 1999; 1 print: letterpress, color; on sheet 41.8 x 53.3 cm. (Box 1, Folder 37)